Finding Aid for the Livingston Gearhart Collection of Scores, 1930-1996
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Livingston Gearhart Collection of Scores, 1930-1996
Mus. Arc. 23.2
Gearhart, Livingston
34 boxes ( 676 folders )
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The Livingston Gearhart Collection of Scores contains compositions and arrangements by Gearhart in published and manuscript forms, as well as sketches and incomplete works. It also contains published scores by other composers annotated by Gearhart.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Livingston, Pamela, and Fritz Gearhart.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Livingston Gearhart was born in Buffalo, New York December 31, 1916. His mother was Lillian Hawley Gearhart, a pianist who had studied for a year under Theodor Leschetizky in Vienna. As a child Gearhart studied piano, oboe, violoncello, and sang in church choirs in Buffalo and New York City. He graduated from high school in East Orange, New Jersey in 1935. He entered Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia in 1935 as an oboe student of Marcel Tabuteau. In his second year he switched his major to study composition with Rosario Scalero and piano with Nadia Reisenberg.
Gearhart sailed to Paris aboard the Normandie in 1937. With generous support from a wealthy American expatriate, he was able to enroll at the Conservatoire Américain de Fontainebleau where he studied music theory and composition with Nadia Boulanger. He was awarded the school's 2nd prize (no first prize was awarded that year) in the Prix Stovall composition competition in 1937. While in Paris he also met Igor Stravinsky, Darius Milhaud, Robert Casadesus, pianist Isidore Philipp, and his future wife and duo-piano partner, Virginia Clotfelter. He and Virginia performed their debut in Paris February 1, 1939 at the Salle Chopin. They received good reviews and were then able to give concerts in other French and Swiss locations until the conditions of World War II caused them to return to the United States.
Virginia Clotfelter adopted the professional name Morley and married Gearhart February 28, 1940 in New York City. They worked at numerous venues, including the Hotel Brevoort and the club, Ruban Bleu, both operated by Herbert Jacoby. The pair spent the summers of 1942 and 1943 as Artists-in-Residence at Morley's alma mater, Mills College in Oakland, California. While there Gearhart was able to study composition with Darius Milhaud. The Budapest String Quartet was also in residence at Mills College during those years and Gearhart and Morley formed friendships with quartet members Alexander and Mischa Schneider. The Morley Gearhart duo was very successful, performing works by Milhaud, Norman Dello Joio, David Diamond, and Stravinsky's Concerto per due pianoforte soli.
The duo received contracts with Columbia Concerts and the Fred Waring Show that extended from 1943-1954. During 1941 to 1954, the two-piano team of Morley and Gearhart performed over 2000 concerts throughout the US and Canada in addition to recording for Columbia Masterworks and Decca Records. Included among the many concert dates was a performance by the duo at the White House for President Dwight D. Eisenhower in 1953. During this period Gearhart also worked as a staff arranger for the Fred Waring Show.
A two-CD retrospective released in 2001, Morley and Gearhart Rediscovered by Ivory Classics, features 22 of Gearhart's two-piano arrangements. Some of these arrangements survive at Penn State in their collection, Fred Waring's America. In many cases Gearhart never fully wrote out his part of a duo so no written arrangement survives.
Livingston Gearhart's output contains several collections written for pedagogical purposes. The first of Gearhart's these works to be published was Clarinet Sessions in 1945. That was followed by similar collections for trumpet, violin, flute, and duos. Gearhart's entire compositional and arranging output includes 400-500 works (counting individual works within the collections).
Gearhart returned to Buffalo in 1955 and was appointed to the faculty of the music department at the University of Buffalo. After a divorce from Virginia Morley, he married violinist and conductor Pamela Gerhart (not a misspelling) in 1955. He taught various courses in keyboard, theory, and orchestration until his retirement in 1985.
Livingston Gearhart had four children: Paul, born to Virginia Morley Gearhart; Kim, Martha, and Fritz, born to Pamela Gearhart. Livingston Gearhart died in Buffalo at the age of 79 on July 14, 1996.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 676 folders. As part of the original collection, there are 257 folders containing manuscript and published scores of Livingston Gearhart’s compositions and arrangements, 79 folders containing published scores by other composers annotated for performance by Gearhart, and 5 folders containing sketchbooks or workbooks with various musical exercises, sketches, and other works. Excluding the annotated scores and the scores added after original processing was completed, there are approximately 178 folders containing manuscript materials and 84 folders containing printed materials. Of the printed works, approximately 69 were published by Shawnee Press. Gearhart composed his works between 1930 and 1996 but five of his compositions in the collection were published after his death in 1997. His son Fritz Gearhart and wife Pamela Gearhart did extensive work to organize materials and edited several for publication.
The manuscript scores document Gearhart’s work from sketches through different versions to the finished, final version of a work. Most of these are in Gearhart’s hand with a small percentage being copied by other people. Many of the scores are accompanied by instrumental parts and explanatory notes of varying lengths by either Livingston,Pamela, or Fritz Gearhart. These notes often provide details about the background and history of works.
A major component of Gearhart’s output consists of his approximately 119 arrangements. These include arrangements chiefly made for didactic purposes for various instrumental combinations, arrangements for two pianos, many of which were used by Gearhart in his performances with Virginia Morley during their years as a piano-duo, choral arrangements, and arrangements for band or orchestra. There are other works by Gearhart that are difficult to classify strictly as arrangements due to the extent of Gearhart’s compositional reworking of the material. The titles identified as arrangements draw from a wide range of sources, including works by composers such as Arlen, Bach, Berlioz, Boccherini, Brahms, Brubeck, Debussy, Delius, Fauré, Johann Fischer, Haydn, Holst, J. Rosamond Johnson, Joplin, Lyadov, Macdowell, Mendelssohn, Mozart, Cole Porter, Serge Prokofiev, Purcell, Rachmaninoff, Ravel, Rimsky-Korsakov, Schubert, Stravinsky, and Wolf-Ferrari in addition to traditional and popular tunes such as We wish you a merry Christmas, Star spangled banner, Non nobis, Domine, and Au clair de la lune.
Gearhart’s pedagogical works include several compilations that consist of both original and arranged works. Most of these are in a series he titled Sessions: Bass Clef Sessions, Clarinet Sessions, Duet Sessions, Fiddle Sessions, Flute Sessions, Rhythm Sessions, Sax Sessions, Treble Clef Sessions, and Trumpet Sessions. Six of these titles were published by Shawnee Press. Many of the pieces within the compilations were written to provide practice in specific rhythmic and technical elements. Gearhart also devised sets of trick pieces and canons to assist with teaching. Another aspect of Gearhart’s pedagogical work is evident in the many pieces he arranged for use by his wife, Pamela Gearhart, in her work as conductor of the orchestra of the Community Music School of Buffalo and numerous string workshops and musical clinics, including a summer music camp in Huntsville, Alabama called Youth Makes Music. Gearhart also composed a set of nine pieces titled Extraits de mon cahier for pedagogical use by his teacher at Curtis Institute of Music, Marcel Tabuteau.
In addition to separate musical sketches, the collection also contains twelve sketchbooks or workbooks containing original compositions and arrangements as well as studies in harmony and counterpoint written while Gearhart was studying in Paris with Nadia Boulanger. An item of interest is a workbook titled Quodlibets research. It includes a comparative table containing chord structures of various pieces from the folk song, popular, and classical music repertoire. Another item of special interest is a sketchbook containing a two-piano arrangement of Mozart's Quintet in E-flat major K. 614. According to a note by Gearhart the arrangement is by pianist Robert Casadesus and was copied by Virginia Morley.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in six series:
I. Compositions
II. Arrangements, transcriptions, and editions of works by other named composers
III. Compilations and sketchbooks
IV. Annotated scores
V. Manuscript score additions
VI. Published score additions
Container List
- Compositions, 1930-2005, I; Folder 1-114
  Arranged alphabetically by main entry (composer or title). Compositions by Gearhart are under his name alphabetically in the list and then arranged alphabetically by uniform title. Folk song arrangements are listed by the uniform title for the specific song. There are two other composers stated in the list, Philip Klein and Virginia (Morley) Waring. Gearhart was co-composer of both pieces. Those works are stated under the respective composer's name: Klein and Waring. Sketches of untitled or unidentified works are listed under Gearhart's name and then under titles beginning with the word unidentified or untitled.
  The series includes arrangements of works such as folksongs and spirituals not attributed to a single composer. It also includes musical sketches of both complete and incomplete works, with and without titles.
  - Au clair de la lune (Song); arranged Au clair de la lune 1947, 1 ms. score ([5] p.); 32 cm.; Arranged for voice and piano. Cover title. Music formerly attributed to Jean-Baptiste Lully. "For Jacques [Bastard?], 1947"--Cover. Holograph (Pencil). French words. (Box 1, Folder 001)
  - Can I go: spiritual, for two-part male voices with piano accompaniment 1960, 1 score (8 p.); 27 cm.; Alternate title: First line of text: Lord, if I got my ticket. Alternate title: Can I ride. Caption title. Also known by the title, Can I ride. Includes tone syllables to be used as a choral enunciation aid. Duration: 2:45. Delaware Water Gap, Pennsylvania: Shawnee Press English words. (Box 1, Folder 002)
  - Chicka hanka [between 1950 and 1970], 2 ms. scores; 32 cm.; Alternate title: First line of text: Capt'n, go sidetrack yore train. Alternate title: Captain, go sidetrack yore train. Folk song arranged for tenor or baritone solo, TB chorus, and piano accompaniment. Caption title. The two scores differ in rhythmic setting and text. Verso of p. 2 in score B contains notes about harmonics on the string bass. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 003)
  - Christmas carols: arranged for piano, 4 hands [194-?], 1 ms. score ([8] p.); 32 cm.; Title supplied by cataloger. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 004)
    Contents: O come all ye faithful -- Silent night -- Hark the herald angels sing -- Bring a torch Jeanette, Isabella.
  - Gearhart, Livingston Alabama fanfare A la fanfare: trpt, horn, strgs [1973 or 1974], 1 ms. score (8 p.) + 18 ms. parts; 32 cm.; Alternate title: Ala fanfare. Alternate title: Title on accompanying note by Pamela Gearhart: Alabama fanfare. For trumpet, horn, and string orchestra. Cover title. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Holograph (Pencil). Accompanied by note from Pamela Gearhart about the history of the composition (1 leaf; 28 cm); Fanfare (end revised) score for mm. 39-42 ([4 p.]; 32 cm); photocopy of the score and revised ending (6 leaves; 28 cm). (Box 1, Folder 005)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Adventures of a theme (Sketches) Adventures of a theme [between 1976 and 1996], 1 ms. score ([1] leaf); 28 x 31 cm.; Sketch, possibly for string quartet. Caption title. Based on London bridge. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 006)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Air, oboe, English horn Air: Bachianas Buffalorus #2: for ob + c.a. [between 1976 and 1996], 2 ms. scores; 30 x 38-31 cm.; Alternate title: Bachianas Buffalorus #2. Alternate title: Ricercare. For oboes and English horn. Title from accompanying leaf by Pamela Gearhart. Originally received in a folder with Ricercare for 2 oboes and English horn. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Holograph (Pencil); Holograph (Photocopy). Accompanied by 1 photocopied note from Pamela Gearhart (1 leaf). (Box 1, Folder 007)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Alligator Alligator (see you later?) [between 1940 and 1960?], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 32 cm.; Alternate title: First line of text: To see an alligator. For three solo voices (SSA) or women's choir with piano accompaniment. Caption title. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 008)
  - Gearhart, Livingston American hymn [between 1955 and 1958], 1 ms. score (14 leaves); 32 cm.; Alternate title: First line of text: America my native land. For mixed chorus and piano or possibly organ. Caption title. Holograph (Pencil). Accompanied by: typescript poem titled "American Hymn" by Wihla Hutson with annotations in an unknown hand (1 leaf; 28 cm); typescript poem titled "Patriotic Theme" crossed out in pen and retitled "More American Hymn" with annotations in an unknown hand (1 leaf; 28 cm); typescript letter titled "American Hymn" presumably from Livingston Gearhart explaining the composition with a response in an unknown hand dated "3/30/58" and "April 1 1958." (1 leaf; 28 cm). Duration: ca. 3:30. English words presumably by Livingston Gearhart; text setting incomplete. (Box 1, Folder 009)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Bar'chu [196-?], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 32 cm.; Alternate title: First line of text: Bar'chu et adonay hamvorach. For cantor, mixed chorus (SATB), and organ. Caption title. Holograph (Pencil). Hebrew words. (Box 1, Folder 010)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Bayom hahu [196-?], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 32 cm.; Alternate title: First line of text: Bayom hahu yih'yeh adonay. For mixed chorus (SATB) and organ. Caption title. Holograph (Pencil). Hebrew words. (Box 1, Folder 011)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Brigg fair: folk song [between 1940 and 1960?], 1 ms. score (3 leaves); 33 cm. + 1 ms. part ([1] leaf); 28 cm.; Alternate title: First line of text on score: It was on the fifth of August. Alternate title: First line of text on vocal part: Gray the sullen sea beneath. For STB chorus with piano accompaniment. Caption title. Part for solo voice signed by Wihla Hutson. Score and part have different texts. Text of part presumably by Wihla Hutson. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 012)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Canon at major 3rd [between 1976 and 1996], 1 ms. score (1 leaf); 30 x 38 cm. + 1 ms. part (1 leaf); 28 cm.; Alternate title: Canon at major third. Instrumentation not specified on score. Suggested instrumentation at bottom of part: oboe d'amore or clarinet in A with English horn. Caption title from part. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Holograph score (Pencil); holograph part (Photocopy). Accompanied by: list written by Pamela Gearhart of canons by Livingston Gearhart (1 leaf). (Box 1, Folder 013)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Canon at major 6th [between 1976 and 1996], 1 ms. score (1 leaf); 31 x 46 cm. + 2 ms. parts; 28 cm.; Alternate title: Canon at major sixth. Instrumentation suggested at bottom of score: oboe and alto saxophone or English horn, or alto flute and tenor saxophone, or clarinet in A or oboe d'amore and viola. Title from lower margin of score. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Holograph score (Pencil); holograph part (Photocopy). Accompanied by: 2 photocopies of untransposed part (1 leaf each); list written by Pamela Gearhart of canons by Livingston Gearhart (1 leaf). (Box 1, Folder 014)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Canon at minor 3rd [between 1976 and 1996], 1 ms. score ([1] leaf); 30 x 38 cm. + 2 ms. parts; 28 cm.; Alternate title: Canon at minor third. Instrumentation not specified on score. Suggested instrumentation from caption: for oboe d'amore or A clarinet and oboe or oboe and E♭ clarinet. Caption title from part (Photocopy). "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Holograph (Pencil); titled part consists of 1 leaf pencil ms. and 1 leaf photocopy of ms. Accompanied by: list written by Pamela Gearhart of canons by Livingston Gearhart (1 leaf; 30 cm.). (Box 1, Folder 015)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Canon in augmentation on the King's theme [1988], 2 ms. scores; 35 cm. + 1 ms. part; 32 cm.; Alternate title: Caption title from part: Canon on King's theme. Instrumentation not specified on score; suggested instrumentation from caption: for 2 violins or 2 clarinets. Title from caption on score. Based on the theme from The musical offering by J. S. Bach. Two scores include the theme written out on a single staff followed by a version on two staves with the rhythmically augmented line written out. The two scores are written using different rhythmic values. "J.Z. Bach"--Caption of part. "LG 1988"--At bottom of score. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Includes photocopies of both scores and the part. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 016)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Canons, clarinets (2) Canon for B♭ + A clarinets [1988], [2] p. of ms. music; 32 cm.; Title from caption on part. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. "Revision 11/88"--Caption. Holograph (Pencil). Accompanied by: 4 photocopied parts (2 p. each); list written by Pamela Gearhart of canons by Livingston Gearhart (1 p.). (Box 1, Folder 017)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Canons, woodwinds (2) Misc. canons for two winds [between 1976 and 1996], 1 folder (3 ms. scores); 25 x 31, 28-34 cm.; Alternate title: Miscellaneous canons for two winds. Alternate title: Rondo. Title from accompanying leaf. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 018)
    Contents: Rondo for alto and tenor sax -- Untitled canon for oboe d'amore or clarinet in A and oboe or flute, or oboe or flute and E♭ clarinet -- Untitled canon with instrumentation not specified.
  - Gearhart, Livingston Dese bones gwine to rise again: a story of Adam and Eve; cantata jazza: S.A.T.B. with narrator and soloists 1946, 1 score (24 p.); 27 cm.; For SATB chorus with narrator and various soloists with piano accompaniment. Performance notes precede score. East Stroudsburg, Penna.: Shawnee Press (Box 1, Folder 019)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Diogenes: for mixed voices (S.A.T.B.) 1971, 1 score (8 p.); 27 cm.; For mixed voices (SATB) and optional solos with piano and optional guitar accompaniment. Cover title. Includes chord symbols. Duration: ca. 3:00. Delaware Water Gap, Pennsylvania: Shawnee Press (Box 1, Folder 020)
  - Gearhart, Livingston English dance [1930?], 1 ms. score ([1] leaf); 28 cm.; Instrumentation not specified on score; possibly a treble C instrument with keyboard accompaniment. Caption title. "1930?"--Lower margin. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 021)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Extraits de mon cahier: (1937 à 1941) [between 1937 and 1941], 1 folder (8 ms. scores); 32 cm.; Folder contains 9 pieces (solos, duets, trios, and a quintet) for various woodwind combinations. Title from additional cover leaf. "From Tabuteau"--Folder. Holograph (Ink); Holograph (Photocopy). Includes a photocopy of Over a fragment of Franck for 2 unspecified treble instruments (1 leaf; 43 cm.). (Box 1, Folder 022)
    Contents: Mild delirium (for 2 clarinets) -- Dialogue (for 2 oboes) -- Sad improvisation (for 2 oboes) -- Invention (for two oboes) -- Lament (for 3 oboes) -- Tune (for oboe) -- Dance (for two flutes) -- Song without words (II) (for English horn, 2 clarinets and 2 bassoons).
  - Gearhart, Livingston Fanfare in stilo Milhaud [1975], 1 ms. score ([4] p.); 48 cm. + 8 ms. parts; 32 cm.; Alternate title: Caption title from last page of score: Fanfare 7.1. For 3 trumpets, 3 trombones, optional French horn, and percussion. Caption title.* "L Gearhart 1975"--Caption. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Accompanied by: letter from Livingston Gearhart to Jim (1 leaf); 1 note from Livingston Gearhart about the piece (1 leaf); 1 note presumably from Pamela Gearhart (1 leaf). Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 023)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Fanfares, pianos (2), 8 hands, percussion Fanfare [1938], 2 ms. scores + 9 ms. parts; 35 cm.; Alternate title: Gigue. Alternate title: Prelude. For 2 pianos (8 hands) and percussion. Title from cover of 1st piano part. One score includes piano parts and percussion; second score contains percussion parts only. Note from Pamela Gearhart indicates this could be performed as part of a suite. The other works, Gigue and Prelude, are for similar instrumentations. "To Annette Dieudonné, 1938 Paris"--Note from Pamela Gearhart. "Some of the parts copied by Annette Dieudonné, [Nadia] Boulanger's life long assistant"--Note from Pamela Gearhart. Attached to the tambourine part is Marche du Roi William by Jeremiah Clarke, arranged for piano. Manuscript (Ink) and (Pencil) with annotations in red pencil. Accompanied by one note (1 leaf) from Pamela Gearhart. (Box 1, Folder 024)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Fanfares, unspecified instruments (4) Fanfare: concert pitches [between 1976 and 1996], 2 ms. scores; 28-32 cm. + 4 ms. parts; 29-35 cm.; Alternate title: Title on trumpet part: Fanfare: canon 4-in-2. Alternate title: Habañera de Honolulu. Alternate title: Sicilienne. Instrumentation not specified on score. Suggested instrumentation from captions of parts: for pairs of: flutes and alto flutes, alto and tenor saxophones, or trumpets and horns. Caption title from smaller score. Parts written on double staves. Note from Pamela Gearhart, filed with Sicilienne, indicates this could be performed as part of a suite. The other works include Habañera de Honolulu and Sicilienne, both of which are for similar suggested instrumentations. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. "1995 revision. LG"--At bottom of score. Holograph (Pencil), one part with no instrumentation designated is a photocopy. Accompanied by: 2 notes from Pamela Gearhart (1 leaf each; 30 cm). (Box 1, Folder 025)
  - Gearhart, Livingston For the birds: 2 picc [1988], 1 ms. score ([2] leaves); 30 x 38 cm.; Caption title. "LG 7/88"--At bottom of leaf [2] of score. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Accompanied by: 1 ms. score ([4] leaves; 31 cm.) copied in another hand; 5 leaves of ms. sketches (30 x 38 - 31 x 46 cm); note from Pamela Gearhart (1 leaf). Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 026)
  - Gearhart, Livingston Fuga subverta: trio [between 1940 and 1960?], 1 ms. score ([2] p.); 32 cm.; Instrumentation not specified on score. Caption title. "Palestrina"--Inscription in caption but a source in Palestrina's works cannot be identified. "For 3 #2"--Caption. "Livingston Gearhart 1996"--Copyright stamp on every page. Holograph (Pencil). (Box 1, Folder 027)